New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Small Format Photograph and Postcard Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Small Format Photograph and Postcard Collection.
ca. 1870s-1960s.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Unknown.
94 items/.5 linear feet.
For almost one hundred years the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, was the primary means of passenger and freight transportation in Southern New England. Chartered in 1872, this merger between the New York & New Haven and Hartford & New Haven railroads later included the long desired rail link between Boston and New York.
MSS19910133
History
For almost one hundred years the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, was the primary means of passenger and freight transportation in southern New England. Chartered in 1872, this merger between the New York & New Haven and Hartford & New Haven railroads later included the long desired rail link between Boston and New York. Approximately one hundred small independent railroads were built in southern New England between 1826 and the 1880s. By 1904, the majority were absorbed into the vast New Haven system. At its peak in 1929, the New Haven Railroad owned and operated 2,131 miles of track throughout eastern New York, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island.
The local railroad lines that eventually became part of the New Haven system developed in response to local business and transportation needs. Unlike the Western states, where railroads preceded and shaped settlement, in the Northeast they served primarily to link existing towns, businesses, and markets. The New Haven system thus developed as a result of numerous consolidations and mergers. The New Haven traced its founding to 1826, when one of its predecessor companies originated, but the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad was not chartered until 1872. The company followed the pattern of consolidation established by the Pennsylvania Railroad and other companies, particularly after 1889, when major lines in Connecticut, Rhode Island, and southern Massachusetts provided a strong network linking New York and Boston. By 1890, company revenue exceeded $100,000,000 per year, and the New Haven employed 4,000 people to serve twelve million passengers annually.
This success led a wealthy group of New York investors, headed by J. P. Morgan, to seek and gain control of the New Haven's board. In 1903, Morgan installed Charles Mellen as president of the railroad. Together Morgan and Mellen set out to achieve a complete monopoly of transportation in New England. Substantial improvements to the system were made during the Mellen years, including electrification of rail lines between Woodlawn, New York, and New Haven, Connecticut, and construction of a power generating plant in Cos Cob, Connecticut. These accomplishments, however, were overshadowed by Morgan's ambitious schemes to dominate all modes of transportation in New England. Steamboat lines, trolley companies, and other railroad lines were purchased regardless of price and incorporated into the New Haven system.
An investigation of the New Haven's activities by Louis Brandeis in 1907 revealed the overextended railroad was on the verge of financial collapse. Morgan's death in 1913 and Mellen's subsequent resignation brought to a close a stormy period in the New Haven's history.
During the First World War, all of the railroads in the United States, including the New Haven Railroad, were operated by the federal government. After the war, under Edward Pearson, President through 1928, the railroad was able to recover partially, despite increasing competition from automobiles, by sharing in the national economic growth of the 1920s. The company tried to meet this transportation competition by forming the New England Transportation Company, which operated a fleet of trucks and buses. Recovery of the New Haven, however, was cut short by the Depression of the 1930s, and in 1935 the New Haven plunged into bankruptcy. The company remained in trusteeship until 1947, when it returned to private ownership.
A series of struggles for control of the company in the post World War II period severely weakened the management of the company and its ability to adapt to changes in the transportation industry. The completion of the Connecticut Turnpike and other superhighways and the start of air shuttle service between Boston and New York intensified competition. The company's historic liability as a railroad overburdened with many short, costly branch lines further accelerated its decline.
On 7 July 1961, the New Haven Railroad once again went into receivership. A seven year trusteeship period followed, culminating in the absorption of the New Haven in the Penn Central system on 1 January 1969. Three years later the Penn Central itself collapsed into bankruptcy. The former components of the New Haven Railroad were divided among several entities. Freight service was assumed by Conrail when it was formed in 1976, although the Providence & Worcester also provided freight service on portions of the former New Haven, as did a few other operators. Passenger commuter service was funded by the New York Metropolitan Transit Authority and the Connecticut Department of Transportation. Long-haul passenger service was provided by Amtrak beginning in 1971. After 1976 passenger commuter service was operated by Conrail. In 1982, the United States Congress passed legislation that forced Conrail to divest itself of its commuter rail lines. On 1 January 1983, Metro-North Commuter Railroad, under joint ownership of the states of New York and Connecticut, took over all commuter passenger service. Amtrak continued to handle all long-haul passenger service.
The history of the New Haven Railroad reveals a company formed by one of the classic merger and consolidation patterns of the late 19th century, which was later unable to respond effectively to major changes in the transportation industry. The company's rapid growth, collapse, temporary recovery, and final dissolution offer a dramatic story, with government regulation, internal management decisions, and market competition playing important roles in the company's history.
Scope and Content
The NY, NH & H Railroad Small format Photographs/Postcards Collection is a portion of the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad archives. This collection is distinguished from the New Haven Railroad Photograph Collection by virtue of the fact that the prints in the Photographs collection are 8 × 10′ in size and prints in the Small Format collection do not exceed a measurement of 5.5 × 3.5′. This display has led to the practical necessity of housing the two collections in different size boxes.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads, particularly the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Railroads--new England.; Locomotives--New England.
Document Types:
Photographs.; Postcards.
Occupations:
Railroad.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred to Archives & Special Collections with the larger NY, NH & H Railroad Records.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Collection, ca. 1870s-1960s
  - Envelope 1-Cars & Trains
    - Car, Meriden, Waterbury & Connecticut River Railroad Combination 10
    - Car, NH Baggage 5317
    - Car, NH Baggage 5578
    - Car, NH Parlor 2156
    - Car, NH Passenger 1798
    - Car, NH Passenger 1263 (2 prints)
    - Car, NH Passenger 1263, “At Franklin”
    - Car, NH Passenger 1476
    - Car, NH Passenger 1530
    - Car, NH Passenger 1823
    - Car, NH Passenger 7804
    - Car, NH Passenger 8100
    - Car, NH Passenger, 1476 and 1479
    - Train, “Sp.-NY. #65 at Meriden, Conn.”, September 26, 1925
    - Train, N&W Centennial Extra, Locomotive NH 1407, Norwich, CT, May 12, 1940
    - Train, NH “east Wind”, Putnam, CT, July 19, 1953
    - Train wreck, P&E Locomotives 1, “Russel Sage”, and 7. (Postcard)
  - Envelope 2-Locomotives-Not New Haven
    - Gas car, Central New England Railroad 9023 on train 906, Winsted, CT
    - Locomotive, Central New England Railway 126, Hartford, CT
    - Locomotive, Central New England Railway 14, Simsbury, Ct, 1904
    - Locomotive, Central New England Railway 1585, Train 909, Winsted, CT, Spring, 1927
    - Locomotive, Central New England Railway 37, Hartford, CT
    - Locomotive, Connecticut & Passumpsic Railroad 27, “Montreal”, late 1872
    - Locomotive, Connecticut & Passumpsic Railroad,: W.K. Blodgett”, late 1800's
    - Locomotive, Hanover Branch Railroad, “Spark”, circa 1870's (post Card)
    - Locomotive, Hartford and New Haven Railroad 26, “Taurus”. 1867
    - Locomotive, Old Colony 243, at Mansfield, MA, 1893 (Postcard)
  - Envelope 3-Locomotives-New Haven
    - Locomotive, NH 016, New Haven, CT, 1928
    - Locomotive, NH 0353 & 0316, New Haven, CT, 1935
    - Locomotive, NH 0365, New Haven, CT, July, 1949
    - Locomotive, NH 0700 & 0728, Putnam, CT, May 20, 1956
    - Locomotive, NH 0738, “Built 1944”
    - Locomotive, NH 1280, 1932
    - Locomotive, NH 1352, At New London, CT
    - Locomotive, NH 1390
    - Locomotive, NH 1500
  - Envelope 3-Locomotives-New Haven
    - Locomotive, NH1503, 1930
    - Locomotive, NH 1538
    - Locomotive, NH 1589 As Rebuilt, June, 1936 (#1)
    - Locomotive, NH 1589 As Rebuilt, June, 1936 (#2)
    - Locomotive, NH 1918, “Formerly 806” (Post Card)
    - Locomotive, NH 2316
    - Locomotive, NH 3007
    - Locomotive, NH 3016, Putnam, CT, July 19, 1953 (#1)
    - Locomotive, NH 3016, Putnam, CT, July 19, 1953 (#2)
    - Locomotive, NH 202, New Haven, CT, May, 1950
    - Locomotive, NH 304, New Haven CT, about 1950
    - Locomotive, NH 307, 1930
    - Locomotive, NH 3106, Waterbury, CT, 1935
    - Locomotive, NH 3203
    - Locomotive, NH 340
    - Locomotive, NH 340, “Old Numbering”
    - Locomotive, NH 341, “Built 1923”
    - Locomotive, NH 3555
    - Locomotive, NH 416
    - Locomotive, NH 416 and 3210
    - Locomotive, NH 470
    - Locomotive, NH 502, Morris, CT, 1904
    - Locomotive, NH 9, New Haven, CT, July, 1949
  - Envelope 4-Stations, Note: Stations are assumed to be New Haven Railroad unless otherwise indicated
    - Station, Berlin-New Britain, CT, September, 1967
    - Station, Bethel, CT, 1966
    - Station, Branchville, CT, May, 1965
    - Station, Bridgeport, CT, “Old Bridgeport Station Torn Down 1904”
    - Station, Brookfield, CT, 1932
    - Station, Cannondale, CT, October, 1965
    - Station, Canton, CT (Central New England Railroad)
    - Station, Chaplin “in Paul Revere Gordon's Yard, 1965”
    - Station, Cos Cob, CT
    - Station, Crecent Beach and Black Point, CT, June 23, 1929
    - Station, Danbury, CT “and Diesel 2050”, 1963
    - Station, East Derby, CT, “Built 1848, Torn Down 1903” (Postcard)
    - Station, Georgetown, CT
    - Station, Grant's, CT, 1928 (Central New England Railway)
    - Station, Greenwich, CT, about 1870 (Postcard)
    - Station, Greenwich, CT, Eastbound Station, November 20, 1928
    - Station, Greenwich, CT, November 20, 1928
  - Envelope 4-Stations
    - Station, Lawrence's, CT, 1928 (Central New England Railway)
    - Station, Meriden, CT, November, 1968
    - Station, New Canaan, CT, 1940
    - Station, New Canaan, CT, September, 1967
    - Station, New Haven, “Old”...Station-1876-1918”
    - Station, New Haven, CT, “Old Station” (Postcard)
    - Station, New Haven, CT, circa 1851 (Postcard)
    - Station, New London, CT, “Locos 3107 and 1317”, March 22, 1936
    - Station, Putnam, CT, “The Old Depot” (Postcard)
    - Station, Rockland, 1905, (Postcard)
    - Station, Ramford, CT, “Shepaug or Shepaug Valley RR” (Postcard)
    - Station, Springdale, CT, April, 1966
    - Station, Stamford, CT, “old Depot” (postcard)
    - Station, Stamford, CT, 1894
    - Station, Stamford, CT, with “TR. 175 Electric Engine”, May 27, 1950
    - Station, Stonington, CT
    - Station, Talcotville, CT, June 24, 1928
    - Station, Thomaston, CT, June 24, 1928
    - Station, Thompsonville, CT, September, 1967
    - Station, Wallingford, CT, 1949
    - Station, Waterbury, CT, September 21, 1963
    - Station, West Willington, CT, October, 1973
    - Station, Wilton, CT, “From Under Bridge”